人人影视
倾情奉献
翻译
CiciXT这都是啥
木浅薰
翻译
小花豆
ddj
翻译
某豚
磁芯章鱼X
翻译
草草
时间轴
Kallen 今
特效
宝宝
电脑狂人
第一季
第一集
校对&总监
草草
后期
饿得慌
顾问
大伟昔
宕机并烧毁(HCF):
早期电脑命令  执行后将使计算机进入竞争状态
迫使所有指令同时争抢优先权
将无法重新控制电脑
宕机并烧毁(HCF):
早期电脑命令  执行后将使计算机进入竞争条件
迫使所有指令同时争抢优先权
将无法重新控制电脑
今天的讨论延期
Today's discussion is postponed
我们请到了一位特殊嘉宾
as we have a very special guest.
他在IBM个人电脑全球首发中扮演了重要的角色
He's played an instrumental part in the world debut of the IBM PC,
IBM个人电脑即将成为
which is now on the verge of becoming
美国企业的标配
the industry standard for corporate America.
有请乔瑟夫·麦克米伦先生
Please welcome Mr. Joseph MacMillan.
我先问个问题
Let me start by asking a question.
你们中有多少人想成为计算机工程师
How many of you desire to be computer engineers?
很高兴你能赏脸
Glad you could join us.
手不要放下来
Keep your hands up, keep your hands up.
下面我将列出几项领域
Now I'm going to list off several categories.
如果哪一领域自己没有实践经历
When you hear a category you don't have hands-on experience in,
请把手放下
put your hand down.
软件开发
Software design.
硬件软件集成
Hardware/software integration.
电路设计  微处理
Circuity design. Microprocessing.
固件设计  超大规模的集成电路
Firmware design. Very large-scale integration.
好笑吗
Something funny?
我觉得你不懂那个
I don't thing you really know what that is.
为什么
Why?
因为懂的人不这么说
Because nobody who knows what it is calls it that.
VLSI  对吗
"VLSI." How's that?
操作系统
Operating systems.
可编程只读存储器配置和逻辑控制器设计
P-ROM configuration and PLC design.
个人电脑设计  很好
Personal computer design. Very good.
说说十年之后
Now, tell me one thing that will be true
计算机行业会如何
about computers 10 years from now.
全智能计算机将能
Well, fully intelligent machines
模拟神经元活动  从而更完美地复制...
will simulate the actions of neurons, more closely replicate...
够了  谢谢  你说
Okay, thanks. You.
电脑之间会通过标准协议
Uh, computers will be connected together across one network
连成网络
with a standard protocol.
-像电话一样吗  -当然了
- Like phone lines. - Obviously phone lines.
-你叫什么  -卡梅伦
- What's your name? - Cameron.
卡梅伦·豪伊
Cameron Howe.
那么你今年毕业
So, you graduate this year.
之后找个工作  做程序员吗
You land a job, become a programmer for what,
你想做什么  微机码  个人电脑  电子游戏
what do you wanna do? Microcode? PCs? Video games?
要25分硬币吗
Do you need a quarter?
-有了  -聪明
- Got it. - Nice.
我想加入里根的战略防御计划
I want to work for Reagan's Strategic Defense Initiative
把导弹送上天呢
and put missles in space.
你是不敢直截了当地回答我吗
Are you afraid to give me a straight answer?
直截了当吗  让我想想
A straight answer? Uh, let's see.
我在这里学的东西早过时了
Everything I'm studying here is so totally 10 years ago
但凡有点分量的人都不会在意的
that no one who matters pays attention to anything I do.
-我在意啊  -是  但你算哪号人
- I'm paying attention. - Yeah, but do you matter?
能给我们拿两杯酒吗
Hey, can we get two more?
我要是号人物  你看得出吗
Would you know if I did?
你这是想干什么  面试我吗
What is this anyway, some kind of job interview?
也许是  也许不是  看你了
Maybe, maybe now. Depends on you.
你还没回答我的问题呢
You still haven't answered my question.
我想做什么有关系吗
Does it even matter what I want to do?
整个行业根本就是一群人
God, this is an industry built on people
互相剽窃彼此的无聊点子
ripping off each other's boring-ass ideas.
SCP抄袭CP/M的代码  微软又抄袭SCP
SCP rips off CP/M, Microsoft rips off SCP.
SCP:西雅图计算机产品公司  CP/M:早期最著名的磁盘操作系统
而IBM到处抄  不是吗
Oh, IBM rips off everybody, right?
你还挺会找借口
You've got a lot of excuses.
你还给IBM工作呢
And you work for IBM!
电脑潜力巨大  应当充分发挥
Hey, computers could be more. They should be.
你们就一直造计数机吗
You build counting machines,
造了70年了还固步不前吗
the same thing you've done for the last 70 years.
我不给IBM工作
I don't work for IBM.
来啊
Come on.
这不代表你得到工作了
This doesn't mean you get the job.
你是说我们还不算相爱吗
You mean we're not in love?
克拉克
Clark.
达拉斯郡警局
没哪个牢房关得住我
Ain't no jail cell can hold me.
好啦
Come on.
你没必要把孩子也带来吧
You didn't have to bring the kids.
我觉得有
I think I did.
我就是多喝了点
Look, I had one too many drinks.
一不留神
It got away from me.
不会再这样了
It won't happen again.
抱歉
Sorry.
你的工作没丢吧
You still have a job?
当然没丢
Of course I do.
反正他们本来也不在意我
They could care less about me anyway.
还记得在演示上
Remember at the demo
我们去开  可就是开不开
when we went to turn it on and it wouldn't turn on?
戈登
Gordon...
1979年还好好的  可一到1980年
It's like, 1979 was good, but then 1980 came
一切都变了
and it was like, whoa...
怎么回事啊
what happened, you know?
我只知道  你还有四个小时就得上班了
What I know is that you need to be at work in four hours.
四个小时
Four.
还有你爸  他说
Then your dad... your dad said,
我们不能再借你们钱了
"We can't lend you any more."
他也没有恶意
And he wasn't being mean.
就那么站在厨房里看着我
He was just in his kitchen looking at me,
于是我说  好吧  盖瑞
and I said, "Okay, Gary."
你醉了  你现在最好还是闭嘴吧
You're drunk, so the best thing you could do right now is to shut up.
我知道IBM的能耐
I know what IBM is.
但我也了解它的缺点
I also know what IBM ain't,
它最慢最贵最不好使
and everything that ain't IBM is cheaper, faster, and better,
所以我们才有活路
and that's what this company lives by.
约翰  日立当时也这么想
Well, John, that's what Hitachi thought.
还有慧聪研究  全国现金出纳机
And Burroughs and NCR
霍尼韦尔和数据控制
and Honeywell and Control Data.
我知道那些IBM打垮的公司
No, I know all the companies that IBM has crushed,
卡迪夫电子不会重蹈他们的覆辙
and Cardiff Electric ain't one of 'em. It won't be.
你好像很肯定嘛
You sound pretty sure about that.
看看你
Look at you.
没换衣服却换了领带
Same suit, different tie.
达拉斯离阿蒙克  纽约远着呢  小子
You know, Dallas is a long way from Armonk, New York, son.
-这可不是巧合  -您说的很对
- That's no accident. - I couldn't agree with you more.
但我或许就是不想再那样做事了
But maybe I'm a guy who's done doing business like that.
我认为  卡迪夫电子作为二线公司
Maybe I see Cardiff Electric as a mid-majo
到了更进一步的时候了
ready to take the jump
而我则是能为你创造神话的营销高手
and myself as the heavy hitter you need
带领你的销售团队
to legitimize your sales force,
推广你的公司  占领整个地区
this company, this region.
我只需要一个
I just need someone to come in here
能拉起销售额的人  乔
and blow the balls off the numbers, Joe.
这么说吧  就是系统软件  简单明了
I will tell you this... it's system software, straight up.
不是应用程序  下一代计算机之类的垃圾
No application, no next-gen PC garbage.
也许不炫目  但能赚钱
It ain't sexy, but it sure as hell make us some serious money.
-那我再合适不过了  -我可没看出来
- Then I'm your guy. - Don't know if I see it.
你一身东海岸公司的味道
You got East Coast corporate written all over ya.
我不喜欢东海岸
Don't like East Coast corporate.
说得那么牛  你连份简历都没带
Hell, hotshot, you didn't bring in a damn resume.
-这又是什么  -我的报税单
- And what is this? What am I looking at? - My W-2.
第一栏是我在IBM的最后一次工资
Box one is my last reported income at IBM.
这也是我完成200%配额的结果
It's also what 200% of quota looks like.
我是顶尖的
The golden circle.
我能拉动销售额  一向如此
I'll break numbers. I always do.
你听命于我  我是销售部高级副总裁
You answer to me. I'm SVP of sales,
谈不来生意  你就什么都不是
so you're dog shit around here until you close a deal.
-懂吗  -我懂
- Do you understand? - I do.
懂  那就好
I "Do." Good.
就这么定了
Well, we're married.
去创造销售额吧  亲爱的
You may now go break your numbers, darlin'.
卡迪夫电子  公司概览
销售及执行部高级副总裁  约翰·博斯沃思
销售工程师  戈登·克拉克
...刘易斯维尔和卡罗敦路段畅通
...free and clear through Lewisville and Carrollton,
但车流正在变缓...
but starting to slow down...
A16
A-16.
那是我的车位  A16
Hey, that's me. That's my spot, A-16.
戈登·克拉克
A16
A-16!
A-16.
-你来做我这次销售的销售工程师  -太好了
- You're my SE for this sales call. - Oh, fantastic.
坐我车去吧  离着近
We'll take my car, it's closer.
事实就是  我们的系统
Well, the truth is our system's
胜过行业里任何一款畅销产品
are outperforming every top seller in the market.
-那IBM呢  -IBM依然是龙头
- What about IBM? - IBM is IBM,
但我们不分上下  而且我们价格更低
but we're neck and neck and we're cheaper.
差价根本不大
Technically. The difference in cost is negligible.
你们卡迪夫的人似乎是
It just seems you guys at Cardiff
觉得自己造了一辆
think you've built yourselves a fancy race car
值天价的高档跑车
that deserves an outrageous price tag.
又不像蓝色巨人[IBM]有保障
And we get no Big Blue guarantee.
我觉得就没这回事
I don't think there is such a thing.
我可是信了
Well, they had me fooled.
我也是
Me, too.
我以前在那里工作
I worked there.
在那里成长
I grew up there.
我一直相信我们所做的工作
And I was brought up to believe that the work we did,
和设计  对电脑发展的贡献独一无二
the things we built were the singular contribution to computers
将能名垂千古
that history would remember.
很长一段时间我都这么认为
And I believed it for a long time.
很长一段时间  这也的确是事实
For a long time, it was true.
从没有人因为买IBM的产品而被炒  对吧
Nobody ever got fired for buying an IBM, right?
这样做生意也太胆小了吧
What a fearful way to do business.
你所做的安全选择足以让你
You've made just enough safe choices
在行业中生存  但远不够成为行业龙头
to stay alive, but not enough to matter.
这就是你想要的吗
Is that what you want?
你可以做大
You can be more.
你想做大  对吧
You want to be more, don't you?
机会正在流失
The window of oppurtunity is closing.
抓住这次机会吧
This is your chance.
这不是只为了不被淘汰
This is not about not losing.
而是终于有信心
This is about you finally having the confidence
放手一搏  并且确定你不会一败涂地
to walk out on the ledge and know that you're not going to fall.
我们还在说系统软件吗
Are we still talking about systems software here?
阿门  再给这哥们上杯酒
Amen, let's get this guy another drink.
我在乎你的生意  我不会为此道歉
I'm not going to apologize for caring about your business,
即使你的手下不在乎
even if the people who work for you don't.
我再问你一遍
I'll ask you one more time.
你想做大吗
Are you ready to be more?
-还有免费安装...  -戈登  别说了
- There's also free install... - Gordon, please.
我会考虑的
I'll think about it.
这比直接拒绝好多了
Look, it's better than a flat-out no.
听着  应用数据
Hey, man, look, Applied Data
这几年就没买过什么
hasn't bought jack-all from anyone in years.
你解释软件时做得很好
You did a solid job explaining the software,
但我需要你再帮我一个忙
but I need you to do me one favor.
好的
Okay.
下一次我快得手的时候  你要这么做
Next time I move to close, this is what you do.
-怎么做  -闭上嘴
- Okay, what? - You shut up!
妈妈
Mom.
快过来  小鬼  给我个亲亲
Come here, you little monkeys. Give me my kisses.
谢谢  去玩吧
Thank you. Go play.
这是苏打水
It's soda.
妈妈  拼读机不好使了
Mom, Speak & Spell's not working.
怎么了
Well, what's wrong with it?
-打不开  -琼妮弄坏的
- It won't turn on. - Joanie did it.
才不是  海莉弄坏的  她在玩积木
Uh-uh, Haley did it. She was playing with her blocks...
我来看看
Let's see.
琼妮的拼读机打不开了
Joanie's Speak & Spell won't turn on.
按"开"键就好了
Pressing "on" makes it go.
好吧
Okay.
-你能把它修好吗  -我试试
- Are you gonna fix it? - I'm gonna try.
它给你拼好词了吗
Did it give you any good words?
把你难倒了吗
Did it stump you at all?
没有
No.
好吧
Okay.
她往机器上扔积木
She was throwing her blocks at it.
是你的错  你按了"开"键
But you did it. You were pressing "On."
-我不在乎是谁弄坏的  -那样可能会把它弄坏
- I don't care who broke it. - That probably breaked it.
-我就负责把它修好  -不会的
- I'm just gonna get it fixed, okay? - No.
好了  姑娘们  回房间去
Okay, girls, other room, please.
拜托了  多谢
Please? Thank you.
你能帮忙看一下这东西是怎么了吗
You want to take a look and see what's wrong with that?
那是你们公司的产品  不是我们的
They make that where you work, not where I do.
戈登  那你帮我拿一下盐总行吧
Okay, Gordon, do you want to maybe get me the salt?
你能把手伸进
Maybe you could reach into
你旁边大概七英寸处的柜子里
the cabinet about seven inches from your head,
把盐拿出来递到我手里
take out the salt and put it in my hand
好让我做完这道菜
so I can finish cooking this.
你能把盐递给我吗
Do you think you could at least get me the salt?
盐给你
Here's the salt.
谢谢
Thank you.
A16
A16.
《字节》
-干什么  -33页
- What is this? - Page 33.
伙计  如果你觉得这好笑的话
Man, if you think it's funny...
33页
Page 33.
我现在没这个心情  好吗
I'm not in the mood, all right?
你去把头发再吹干点或者什么的吧
Why don't you go blow-dry your hair some more or something?
你不知道你写了什么吗
Don't you realize what you wrote?
你画了一张藏宝图
You wrote a treasure map.
如果你看到那个人了  我想见见他
If you see him around, I wanna meet that guy.
我想和他谈个项目
There's a project I want to discuss with him.
你这是干什么  你为什么要这么做
What are you doing? Why are you doing this?
如此一来  未来掌握在了那些
"This puts the future squarely in the hands
并不只看到当今的电脑
of those who know computers not for what they are,
而能设想未来的电脑的人手里
but for everything they have the potential to be."
什么
What?
你知道这话谁说的吗
You know who said that?
不  我不知道
No, no, I don't.
你说的
You did.
36页  最后一段
Page 36, closing paragraph.
电脑不是终点
Computers aren't the thing.
只是我们达到终点的工具
They're the thing that gets us to the thing.
开放式架构的未来
作者  戈登·克拉克
在电路板上
Over here on the circuit board,
可以看到ROM芯片  就像大脑一样
you've got the ROM chip. That's like the brain
只读存储器
用来记录所有单词
that remembers all the words...
容量有128千比特  那是好多单词呢
128 kilobits worth. That is a lot of words.
这个是真空荧光显示器
And then you've got your VFD display right here.
这是负责显示单词的
That's the part that shows you the words.
这里是语言合成芯片
And the speech synthesizer chip right here,
这块很特别  是妈妈的公司制造的
that is the extra-special one they make where Mommy works.
我来接
I got it.
你好
Hello?
乔·麦克米伦找你
It's somebody named Joe MacMillan.
我们正要出门看电影
We're headed out the door to a movie.
-回头让他打给你  -这块特别芯片是做什么的
- Can I have him call you back? -What does the special chip do?
这个芯片能让机器说话
Oh, um, the chip makes it talk.
就像你和我说话一样
You know, like you and me.
你能让它说话吗
Can you make it talk?
现在不行  丫头
Not right now, kiddo.
琼妮  去准备好出发看电影吧
Hey, Joanie, why don't you go get ready for the movie, 'kay?
他想问你有没有考虑过他的话
He wanted to know if you thought about what he said.
那篇在《字节》上刊登的文章
That article I wrote in "Byte."
怎么了
What about it?
他有些计划
He had some ideas about it.
是吗  什么计划
Oh, yeah? What kind of ideas?
我不知道
I don't know.
不重要
It doesn't really matter.
回家把另外两部《星球大战》看了
Go home and watch the other two "Star Wars"?
想今晚看吗
You wanna do that tonight?
我是乔·麦克米伦
Joe MacMillan.
我们之前通过电话
We spoke on the phone earlier.
你跟踪我过来的
Did you follow me here?
你丈夫是我在卡迪夫电子遇到的最好的销售工程师
Your husband is the best SE I've worked with at Cardiff Electric.
当然  我才在那里工作了一周
Now, granted, I've only been there a week.
我能私下和戈登说句话吗
Do you mind if I borrow Gordon for one second?
-来吧  -外面见
- Come on. - Hey, I'll see you guys outside.
好啊  也许吧  如果爸爸同意的话
Yeah, maybe, if Daddy lets us.
和我一起逆向工程一台IBM个人电脑
Reverse engineer an IBM PC with me.
什么  为什么  目的是什么
What? Why? What would be the point?
因为我想做一台别人没胆子做的电脑
Because I want to build a machine that nobody else has the balls to build.
你是认真的
Wow, you're serious.
听着  这主意很糟
Look, that's a terrible idea.
-为什么  -有很多理由...
- Why? - For such a multitude of reasons that I...
因为这么做是违法的
because it's illegal.
最糟糕的情况是  IBM把我们告倒
Worst-case scenario, IBM sues us into the ground.
卡迪夫发现了  会把我们都扫地出门
Uh, Cardiff finds out, then both of us would be on the street.
苹果  IBM  他们已经占领了市场
Apple, IBM, they have the market sewn up.
还要对付康懋达  坦迪公司和德州仪器
Plus, you got Commodore, Tandy, Texas Instruments.
均为八十年代如日中天的电脑公司
抱歉  但你已经错失良机
I'm sorry, but you missed it.
我们都是
We all did.
戈登  等等
Gordon, wait, wait.
所以我们要以卡迪夫电子的名义做
That's why we do it as Cardiff Electric.
马上能规模化生产
Scale up instantly.
你疯了吗
Are you out of your mind?
博斯沃思和卡迪夫这样的老糊涂绝不会同意...
Buzzards like Bosworth and Cardiff would never go for something...
-那我们就逼他们  -逼他们吗
- So we force their hand. - Force their hand?
你要怎么逼他们
How are you gonna force their hand?
这让我去操心
Let me worry about that part.
爸爸
Dad!
-快来呀  爸爸  -快点
- Come on, Dad! - Hurry!
你有家室吗  乔
Do you have a family, Joe?
我猜也是
That's what I thought.
谢谢  但还是不了
Look, thanks, but no thanks.
那就是乔·麦克米伦吗
So, that was Joe MacMillan, huh?
他跟踪我们一家到电影院  戈登
He stalked our family to the movies, Gordon.
你至少得承认他很疯狂
Could you please acknowledge how crazy that is?
他就是对一件事挺来劲
He's just keyed up about something.
他想要什么
What does he want?
他想搭建一台电脑
He wants to build a computer.
跟你有什么关系
And what does that have to do with you?
戈登
Gordon?
戈登  我们输不起第二次了  你知道的
Gordon, we can't do this again. You know we can't.
听着  我知道  好吗  我知道
Look, I know, okay? I know.
你真知道吗  我之前不得不
Do you know? Because I just had to spread the payments
-划了三张信用卡支付  -老天  唐娜
- for Joanie's next dental visit - Oh, my God, Donna.
琼妮下次的牙齿检查
over three credit cards.
我们真的不能再犯这种错了
It's just literally a mistake that we can't afford to make again.
听着  交响乐是个好主意
Look, the Symphonic was a good idea.
我知道你还这么认为
I know you still think so.
-交响乐是什么  -就是个破电脑
- What's a Symphonic? - It's a silly computer.
妈妈和爸爸搭建的  但不好使
Mommy and Daddy built that didn't work.
交响乐...是你爸爸做过的最棒的东西
The Symphonic... was the best thing your dad ever did.
全力以赴  儿子
你知不知道这玩意有多贵
Do you have any idea how expensive this thing was?
唐娜周末三天带孩子去她哥哥那儿
Donna took the kids to see her brother for the three-day weekend.
我假装发烧...
I faked a fever, so...
把这玩意拆个底朝天吧
let's turn this thing inside out.
个人电脑  和所有其他电脑一样
A personal computer, like any other computer,
只是个装满了电子开关和硬件的空盒子
is just a nothing box full of electronic switches and hardware.
像什么IBM电脑  阿尔泰电脑  苹果二号
You know, the IBM, the Altair, the Apple II...
原理都那个鬼样
it's all the same junk.
随便什么人都能立马在商店买到这些
Anyone can buy all this stuff off the shelf right now.
这就叫"开放式架构"
It's called "Open architecture."
机子里的东西  基本上没一件是IBM的
I mean, IBM, they basically don't own anything inside the machine.
除了芯片
Except the chip.
对  除了芯片上的内容
Yeah, well, except what's on the chip.
BIOS就在这其中一块芯片上  只是不知是哪个
The BIOS is on one of these chips, we just don't know which one.
基本输入输出系统
ROM BIOS是IBM唯一真正设计的部分
The ROM BIOS is the only part of the machine IBM actually designed.
这就是程序所在  奇迹所在
I mean, it is the program, it is the magic.
但是  他们握有版权  只有他们知道工作原理
The bad news is they copyrighted it and they own how it works.
好在  可以算是有办法破解
The good news is there's a way around that, sort of.
逆向工程
Reverse engineering.
对  把示波器给我
Right, grab me the oscilloscope.
还有纸笔  把各引脚电压记下来
And a pen and paper. We need to record these pin voltages.
从集成电路[芯片]内部电路引出与外围电路的接线
这事我有点生疏了
I am a little rusty at this.
开始
Yeah.
正五伏
Plus five?
下一个
Yeah.
-零  -下一个
- Zero? - Mm-hmm.
- Zero. - Mm-hmm.
-正五伏  -下一个
- Plus five. - Yeah.
-零  -下一个
- Zero. - Mm-hmm.
-正五伏  -错了
- Plus five. - No.
-零  -下一个
- Zero. - Yeah.
-正五伏  还是零  -没错
- Plus five? Zero. - Yeah.
-负五伏  -嗯  下一个
- Minus five? - Yeah, yeah.
-零  -下一个
- Zero. - Yeah.
-负五伏  -下一个
- Minus five. - Yeah.
零
Zero.
-下一个  -正五伏
- Yeah. - Plus five?
好了  看看效果吧
That's it. Let's get to work.
很好  把这些数字记下来
All right, write these numbers down.
2-8-0-0...
1-3-1-6...
0-4-5-6...
慢着慢着  记这些干什么
Wait, wait, wait, what am I doing here?
这里记的是地址的数据  明白吗
We're writing down the contents of the addresses, all right?
每组四个小灯代表着一个十六进制数
So each group of four lights represents a hex digit.
我明白十六进制代码是什么
I understand hexadecimal code.
你是怎么从这些灯上读出数字的
How are you getting this from that?
第一行这一组  表示字母B
This first line, that's a B.
两开一闭一开
Two on, one off, one on.
第二行表示字母E
Okay, second line here, E.
-三开一闭  -我懂了  我懂了
- Three on, one off... - Oh, I get it, I get it.
我们需要编译多少个这样的地址
How many of these addresses do we need to transcribe?
65,536.
E421
E-4-2-1.
8-0... c-4... c-2-7-2...
3-8-7-9...
C910
C-9-1-0...
4C
4-c...
1-9-2-1...
6C94
6-c-9-4.
好了  启动显示器吧
All right, fire up the monitor.
我去煮点咖啡
I'm gonna go put on some coffee.
编译完了吗
Are we done?
这一部分弄完了
With this part.
好了
All right...
看看弄对了没
let's see if we got it right.
出现命令行了  好兆头
There's a prompt. That's a good sign.
你还真从大海里捞到针了
You found a needle in a haystack.
先别急  启动打印机吧
Now, hold on. Let's fire up the printer.
还有的忙活呢
We still have a lot to do.
这就是IBM电脑的ROM BIOS
The IBM PC-ROM BIOS.
是汇编语言代码
That's the assembly language code.
现在我们做自己的芯片吧
Now we do our own chip.
这个  我
Well, I mean...
我就说吧
I told you.
你画了张藏宝图
It's a treasure map.
大概吧  但是
Yeah, maybe, but look...
我们得好好喝一杯庆祝一下
Oh, this definitely calls for a toast...
糟了
Oh, shit.
我以为你周一才回来呢
I-I thought you weren't gonna be back till Monday.
今天就是周一
It is Monday.
海莉病了  我还以为她被你传染了
Haley's sick. I figured she caught whatever you had,
但看你这样子  显然是生龙活虎啊
but looking at you now, I can tell that you're not sick at all.
这一堆东西不会全是你买的吧
Would you please tell me that you didn't buy all this?
其实事情是这样的
Maybe I can help explain...
我想跟我丈夫
I'd like to speak to my husband...
单独谈谈
privately.
-亲爱的  听我解释  -我实在不懂
- Honey, just let me explain... - I really don't understand.
-你好歹听我解释下  -你为什么骗我
- Let me just defend myself here. - Why would you lie to me?
我没骗你
Hold on, I did not lie to you
-我没骗你啊  -你就是骗了
- about anything. - You did, you lied.
-我没骗你  -戈登你又回老路上去了
- No, I did not lie to you. - Gordon, this is going backwards.
这才是我真正想做的事
This right here, this is what I want to do with my life!
是啊  可你知道你在拿什么冒险吗
Yes, but don't you realize what you're risking?
你知道自己现在拥有什么吗
Don't you realize what you have now?
那不够
Well, it's not enough.
好吗  很抱歉  但那不够
Okay? I'm sorry, it's not enough.
好吧
Okay.
对我来说  这一直都足够了
Well, it always has been enough for me.
唐娜  别这样
Come on, Donna, don't be like that.
但毕竟我没有一心认定自己是
But I guess I never had the burden of believing
被误解的天才
that I was some misunderstood genius.
妈妈送你去上床睡觉
Let's put you to bed.
-约翰  -没空
- John? - Nope.
抱歉  这电话你得接
I'm sorry, but I think you'll wanna take this.
老婆今晚做肉排呢
Mama makin' pork chops tonight.
是IBM
It's IBM.
我是博斯沃思
Bosworth here.
约翰  我是戴尔·巴特勒
John, it's Dale Butler,
北美销售部高级副总裁
Senior Vice President of Sales, North America.
有什么事吗  戴尔
What can I do you for, Dale?
我有个手下在你那儿
You got one of my boys down there.
是啊
Why, yes, we do.
麦克米伦
MacMillan.
人挺有意思
Interesting fella.
可以说我很高兴他还活着
I guess I can say it's good to know he's alive.
怎么说
How so?
乔去年三月离开了公司
Joe walked out the front door of our offices last March.
然后呢
And?
再也没回来
And he never came back.
我有点糊涂了  戴尔
You lost me, Dale.
这一年多  没人有乔·麦克米伦的消息
No one has seen or heard from Joe MacMillan in more than a year.
我们都报警了
We even filed police reports.
我们听说他去给你工作之前
Up until we caught wind he was working for you,
还一直以为他死了  没想到是这样
we believed the worst, but here we are.
他这人有问题  约翰
He's damaged goods, John.
真希望我能早点给你提个醒  现在大概太迟了
I wish I could've warned you, but now it might be too late.
怎么说
How so?
丽贝卡·泰勒  我公司法律顾问也在这儿
I'm here with Rebecca Taylor, our in-house legal counsel.
你好  约翰
Hi, John.
现在有个问题
We've got a problem.
你俩  给我坐下
You two... sit down.
这位是内森·卡迪夫
This here is Nathan Cardiff.
你毁掉的公司是他的
He owns the company you destroyed.
我们刚跟IBM的律师团和你之前的上司
We just got done with a two-and-a-half-hour jaw with
戴尔·巴特勒谈了两个半小时
IBM's legal team, including your old boss, Dale Butler.
是吗  他怎么样了
Oh, yeah? How's he doing?
他好得很呢
Oh, he's doing pretty splendid,
因为蓝色巨人就要把我们告到破产
given the fact that Big Blue is gonna liquidate this company
补偿他们数千万的损失
to the tune of several dozen million dollars in legal damages
全拜你们两个盗窃人家
because two idiot children in our employ
旗舰产品的熊孩子所赐
decided to rip off their flagship product.
先生  其实不是那样的
Sir, that wasn't the idea.
我们没想给公司惹麻烦
We did this solely on our own.
你们怎么想的无所谓
It turns out that doesn't matter...
相信我  我们本打算把你们扔出去喂狼的
and, believe me, we tried to feed you to the wolves, boys.
但麦克米伦在IBM工作过
But because MacMillan here worked at IBM
而你们俩搞那个小项目时都已是我们的员工
and you two were in our employ at the time of your little project,
所以无论好赖  那个项目都属于我们公司了
that project is ours now, for better or worse.
赖  绝对是赖
Worse, in this case.
巴特勒和那个女人  泰勒  明天就要来
Butler and that woman Taylor are headed down here tomorrow.
先生  IBM是怎么知道的
Sir, how the hell did IBM find out about this?
我告诉他们的
I told them.
你就这么强迫他们
That's how you force their hand?
你给IBM通风报信
You call IBM?
让大家都冷静一下就好了
Just let everybody cool off.
我妻子就担心...
This is exactly what my wife...
乔  看着我  我跟你不一样
Joe, look at me. I'm not like you, okay?
我有老婆孩子  有按揭
I have a wife, kids, a mortgage, okay?
我本来好好的  你非要把那篇破文章拿出来
I was fine until you threw that stupid article in my face
给了我...
and gave me some...
什么  我给了你什么  戈登
What? What did I give you, Gordon?
-去你妈的  乔  -很好  生气吧
- Oh, go to hell, Joe. - Good! Get angry, get angry!
找出点感觉来  就像在车库里那样
Feel something, like you did in that garage,
因为只有这样我们才能得到我们想要的
because this is the only way we get what we want.
没什么"我们"可言  乔
There is no "We," Joe.
我们现在是一条船上的了
There is now.
两年前我去了计算机分销商展览
I was at COMDEX two years ago.
我看到了交响乐的展示  它超越了时代
I saw the Symphonic demo. It was ahead of its time.
那是当时  现在我们在这儿  一年后
That was then, this is now... and a year from now,
你会感谢我的  你是个建造者  戈登
you're gonna thank me. You're a builder, Gordon.
我不是  我现在不是了
No, I'm not, okay? Not anymore.
给我听明白
All right? Get that through your head.
-好极了  -好棒
- Yeah. - Yes.
我觉得你可能需要休息一下
I figured you needed a break.
爸爸  你修好了
Daddy, you fixed it!
是啊  打开吧
Yeah, well, turn it on.
你好  琼妮
Hello, Joanie.
你怎么让它喊我名字的
How'd you get it to say my name?
我编了程
Well, I programmed it.
拼个什么给我听听
Now spell something for me.
爸...爸
D-a-d-d-y.
那是什么意思
What's that spell?
听我说  我最近很差劲
Look, I've been awful.
真抱歉
I'm sorry.
我知道你觉得你需要这个
I know you think you need this.
不管这究竟是什么  我应该是拦不住你
And whatever it is, I'm pretty sure I can't stop you.
我知道  但我已经停手了
Yeah, I know. I've already stopped.
电脑  我的工作
Computers, my job...
都不重要
none of that matters.
离了你都不重要了
Not without you.
去做吧
Build it.
不管你想做出个什么来  去做吧
Whatever it is you're dreaming of, build it.
我知道你能创造奇迹
I know you can make it great.
但你听好
But here's the deal.
如果你要跟乔·麦克米伦搭档
You wanna partner with Joe MacMillan...
那么在家里  你要做我的搭档
then you partner with me and this family.
好
Yeah.
没问题
Deal.
我们为什么不能炒了这俩混蛋
Why can't we fire these peckerheads?
那样你就会输了官司
Because then you'll lose this lawsuit.
开除他们  搁置他们的项目
Fire them, shelve their work,
那么就等于承认有罪
you're essentially admitting guilt.
那么我们怎么办  巴瑞
Okay, so what's the solution, Barry?
把项目合法化
We legitimize the project.
-什么  -反其道而行之
- What? - Go the other way.
我们就说卡迪夫电子公司
We say Cardiff Electric as a company
本来就在研发个人电脑
has been pursuing PC development all along.
我不明白这能解决什么...
I don't see how the hell that'd solve any...
你拿克拉克对BIOS芯片的研究
You take Clark's findings on the BIOS chip,
找个工程师建造一个运行原理
you tell an engineer to build a unit that operates and performs
完全相同的芯片  但别告诉他怎么做
in exactly the same way, but you don't tell him how to do it.
我们手下怕是没有一个工程师
Hell, I don't think we have one engineer
能凭空造出一个BIOS芯片
capable of building a BIOS from scratch
大概除了这位大明星
other than "Sonny Bono" over here.
我们不能用他  或是其他任何目前的员工
And you can't use him or any other engineer we currently employ.
还得另外雇吗
So we have to hire?
是的  还得是个跟我们和IBM都没关系
Yes, someone who doesn't know us or IBM
而且没看过这份资料的人
and certainly hasn't seen the contents of this binder.
总之  法律规定
Essentially, all the law stipulates
他不能亲自插手建造芯片
is that he can't be hands-on in the actual chip creation.
-我们还不能炒了他们  -对  现在不行
- And we can't fire them. - No, not right now.
那么我们的出路就是真建一台克隆电脑吗
So we get out of this by actually building a PC clone?
这就是你的救命高招吗  巴瑞
This is your brilliant idea to save our hides, Barry?
老天爷啊
For God's sake, man!
不是
No.
其实  这是麦克米伦的主意
Actually, it was MacMillan's.
你个兔崽子
You son of a bitch.
你昨天怎么不说
Now, why didn't you tell me about this yesterday?
我得让你别无选择
I needed you to exhaust your options
那样你才会认真对待
so that you would take this one seriously.
你知道你这是拿多少人的前途开玩笑吗  小子
Do you know how many futures you're toying with here, son?
售卖系统软件
Selling systems software,
我或许能给你们赚几十万
I probably would've made you a couple hundred thousand...
你给我听着  小子  听好了
You listen to me, boy! You listen to me!
我佩服你的坚持
I admire your tenacity,
但你少跟我说你这是在帮我忙
but I draw the line at you claiming that you did me a favor.
别搞砸了
Don't screw this up.
在德州  你拿别人的生计冒险
'Cause in Texas, you put a man's livelihood on the line
然后又半途而废
and you don't follow through,
那就别再琢磨找新工作了
there's not gonna be another new job
因为到时都没人能找到你的尸体埋在哪
'cause ain't nobody gonna be able to find where you're buried.
有什么话想说吗  戈登
You've got something to say, Gordon?
没有  先生
No. No, sir.
我们去哪再找个工程师来
Where are we gonna find this new engineer?
来不及了  IBM的律师团明天一早就到
We needed him yesterday. IBM legal's here first thing tomorrow.
-我需要时间审查候选人  -没时间了
- I need time to vet a candidate. - We don't have time.
你觉得IBM现在正闲着吗
You think IBM is just sitting around on their asses?
我们现在有谁
Who do we have right now, huh?
现在有什么人吗
Who do we have right now?
下一局了
Next game.
搞什么啊  你都打了一个多小时了
What the hell? You've been on for over an hour.
别碰我
Get your hands off me, man.
我们接到投诉了
We're getting complaints.
难以置信  你给我滚
Unbelievable. You're gone.
滚
Go!
回见了  鬼婆娘
Later, spooky bitch.
你说什么
What?
够了
That's enough!
放我下来
Put me down!
-滚开  -放开我
- Come on! - Let go of me!
法西斯
Fascist!
天呐
Oh, Jesus.
不是吧
No.
怎么了
What?
这下可好
Great.
你知道我上过他吧
You know I screwed him, right?
我们都成熟点对待这事吧
Let's be adult about this.
你就喜欢对我居高临下  是吧
You love talking down to me, don't you?
我们还有几千个其他的选择
Look, there are a thousand other engineers we can get.
最好是找个你没睡过的
Preferably one you haven't bedded down with.
你是谁来着
Who are you again?
我是四天内就破解了引导程序的人
I'm the guy who figured out the boot code in four days.
你有什么本事
What have you done?
你听到了  我们有几千个其他选择
You heard him... A thousand other engineers.
不
No.
你肯定需要我  否则你也不会来找我了
You need me, otherwise you wouldn't be here.
你想要什么
What do you want?
我要你拿着你的机会
I want you to go dangle your little opportunity
去别人面前晃
in someone else's face.
那你怎么还没走
Then why are you still here?
我想看看我当初的错误判断
I wanted to see what I was so wrong about the first time.
我对那事很后悔
I regret that happened.
很抱歉你对伤害我的感情感到难过
I'm sorry you feel bad for hurting my feelings,
但别担心  你没伤着什么
but don't worry, you didn't.
本来不该走到那一步的  我是在物色人才
It wasn't supposed to be personal. I was scouting you.
就为了这个机会
Scouting you for this exact moment.
别  等等
No, wait.
这事太重要  不能有差错
This is too important to get wrong.
有点分量的人都不在意  不是吗
"No one who matters pays attention," Right?
别推销了
Okay, stop selling me.
我不需要你
I don't need you.
你觉得我不明白吗
You think I don't see it?
如果成功  我能飞黄腾达
This takes off, I write my own ticket,
但如果出了岔子  我就成了大学辍学生
but if it goes wrong, I'm a college dropout
修录像机每小时才挣3块25分
repairing VCRs for $3.25 an hour,
抱歉了  我得权衡一下
so forgive me for weighing my options.
瞧
See?
这么想才成熟
Now you're thinking like a professional.
你能给我多少钱
How much money would you give me?
初级工程师  毫无经验  两万
Junior engineer, no experience... 20 grand.
两倍
Double it.
我老婆在德州仪器才挣一万五
My wife makes 15 at TI.
那我替她遗憾
Well, then I feel sorry for her.
行不行
So?
你怎么决定  乔
What's it gonna be, Joe?
请如实回答
Answer honestly.
这是要做法律记录的
This is for legal record.
如果回答不属实可能被控作伪证  明白吗
False answers put you at risk of perjury, you understand?
抱歉  你得回答"是"或"我知道"
I'm sorry, you have to answer "Yes" Or "I do."
是的  我知道
Oh, yes, I do.
你是否曾试图反汇编或拆析
Have you ever attempted to disassemble or deconstruct
国际商业机器  俗称IBM的
any product manufactured by International Business Machines,
任何产品
more commonly known as IBM?
没有
Uh, no, I have not.
你是否曾试图逆向工程
Have you ever attempted to reverse engineer
任何IBM的产品或设备
any product or equipment made by IBM?
没有
No, I have not.
你是否曾受雇于任何公司或企业
Have you ever attempted to reverse engineer
进行任何微芯片  微码
any microchips, microcode, or any computer hardware
或计算机硬件的逆向工程
while under the employ of a business or corporation?
没有
No, I have not.
欢迎
Well, welcome...
登上你们划过的
to the tiniest, leakiest lifeboat...
最小  漏得最严重的救生艇
you ever tried to paddle to shore in.
我让人算了账
I had some numbers run,
看来要做个人电脑光是入门
looks like this PC business is gonna cost us upwards of
就得花上多达两百万以上
a couple million dollars just to get in the door.
所以为了达到能开始卖东西
So, in order to reach that perfect world
而不是躲避追兵的
where we actually start selling things
理想的状态
rather than running from the bogeyman,
我们得定点规矩  一  别扯淡
there will be some rules. One, no bullshit.
抱歉  怎么叫扯淡
Sorry, what constitutes bull...
我说是扯淡就是扯淡
Whatever I damn say it is.
二  工作时间是会议结束到你进坟墓
Two, hours are now from when this meeting is done until when you die.
三  我知道我现在不能解雇你们
And three, I know I can't fire any of you yet,
但那样一来  你们也不能辞职
but that also means you can't leave,
所以我哪天要是心情不好
so if I need to stomp on one of y'all's heads
想拿你们撒气
to feel better about my morning shave,
你们就只能忍着了
whoa, you're gonna have to find a way to deal with that.
明白了吗
Do you understand?
到底谁是我老板啊
So, who's my boss or whatever?
-我  -我
- Me. - Me.
IBM来了
IBM is here.
听着  你们把谎编圆了
Listen, keep your stories straight.
你们今天要说一天了
You're gonna be reciting them all day.
乔  还有件事
Joe, one more thing.
IBM说
According to IBM,
你失踪了一年多
you've been on the side of a milk carton for about a year.
是啊  我雇了你  没查过你的底
Yeah, I hired you. I didn't check your references,
不管你是想干什么  我脱不了干系了
so whatever this is, son, I'm on the hook for it.
你懂吗
You understand?
懂
Yeah.
我在这儿干了22年了
I've worked here for 22 years.
我把公司建成了如今的样子
I helped build this company into what it is.
你在我自己家逼得我走投无路
And you backed me into a corner in my own home?
我永远不会忘记这一点的
I'm never... I'm never gonna forget that.
永远不会
Never.
我会去查你祖宗十八代
I'm gonna root through your closets, boy.
我会利用你的每一个秘密
Oh, I'm gonna pull every loose thread.
-你好吗  戴尔  -见到你真高兴
- How are you? Dale. - Good to see ya.
见到你真高兴
Good to see you.
泰勒小姐  我是约翰·博斯沃思
John Bosworth, Miss Taylor.
我们通过电话
We spoke on the phone.
这边请
This way.
老天爷啊
Holy shit.
你是想证明什么啊
What are you trying to prove with all this?